Finding Aid for the Synanon Foundation Records LSC.0342
UCLA Library Special Collections
Synanon Foundation records
circa 1956-1987
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0342
341.0 linear feet (564 boxes, 118 cartons, and 32 boxes)
Synanon was founded by Charles Dederich, Sr. in 1958. Synanon's detoxification therapy attracted wealthy drug and alcohol abusers with chapters in San Francisco, Tulare and Marin Counties, Detroit, and as far as Germany and Malaysia. The collection consists of correspondence, recordings, films, video tapes, photographs, and printed materials related to the Synanon Foundation.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIO AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audio and audiovisual materials. Audio and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of some audiovisual materials are available for viewing in the Library Special Collections reading room.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of The Synanon Church, Incorporated, 1993.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9932224023606533
Biographical / Historical
Synanon was founded by Charles Dederich, Sr. in 1958; originally named TLC (Tender Loving Care Club), the group was renamed Synanon and had its headquarters in Santa Monica, California; Synanon's detoxification therapy attracted wealthy drug and alcohol abusers, and eventually the organization became a $30 million nonprofit organization; chapters sprang up in San Francisco, Tulare and Marin Counties, Detroit, and as far as Germany and Malaysia; Dederich declared Synanon a religion in 1974; Dederich was forced to give up control of Synanon in 1979 after pleading no contest to conspiracy to commit murder; Synanon quickly lost its popularity thereafter.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of the records of the Synanon Foundation. Includes correspondence, recordings, films, video tapes, photographs, and printed materials.
Related Oral Histories
The following oral history is available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Seven voices from Synanon [oral history transcript] / Charles Dederich, Charles Hamer, Bettye Coleman, Monte Morton, James Middleton, Arlene Hefner, and Reid Kimball, interviewees. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1962. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Synanon Foundation
Related Materials
S. Guy Endore Papers (Collection 279). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Synanon Oral History Interviews These oral histories are a project of The Synanon Archive Trust.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Synanon Foundation records (1 item).
Audiotapes.; Group psychotherapy -- Archives.; Detoxification (Substance abuse treatment) -- Archives.; Dederich, Chuck; Synanon (Foundation)--Archives.
- Archives
  - Miscellaneous statements re Synanon through Synanon v. Hearst - pleadings. (Box 416)
  - Pleadings (loose) Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner (folder 1) through Examiner miscellaneous (folder 1 of 3). (Box 417)
  - Examiner miscellaneous (folder 2 of 3) through Interrogatories and responses (loose) Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner (folder 3 of 4). (Box 418)
  - Interrogatories and responses (loose) Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner (folder 4 of 4) through Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner plaintiff's first set of interrogatories #4-12. (Box 419)
  - Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner plaintiff's first set of interrogatories #A-13, A-75 through Synanon v. Hearst - loose material case. (Box 420)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - loose material re case 6 folders. (Box 421)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - loose material re case 6 folders. (Box 422)
  - Permanent outcard through Synanon v. Hearts - tapes: Faucette interview (w/transcripts). (Box 423)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - jury instructions through Synanon v. Hearst - loose pleadings - Dirty Tricks case (folder 3 of 3). (Box 424)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - loose pleadings - Dirty Tricks case through Pleadings (loose) Dirty Tricks case (folder 3 of 3). (Box 425)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - loose pleadings - Dirty Tricks case (folder 3 of 3) through Synanon v. Hearst - loose pleadings - Dirty Tricks case (folder 2 of 3). (Box 426)
  - Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner - working papers through Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner - petition for hearing in Supreme Court re CED & Sorking. (Box 466)
  - Writ file - Patterson's petition for writ of prohibition through Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner - Rob Patterson's petition for writ of prohibition. (Box 468)
  - Synanon v. San Francisco Examiner - registry of charitable trusts through Correspondence - miscellaneous. (Box 469)
  - Chico v. Synanon - statement of Liz & Tony Giglio through Working papers. (Box 470)
  - Judge & juries through Synanon v. Hearst - investigations requests & reports (151 - 200). (Box 471)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - investigation requests & reports (201 - 250) through [no title]. (Box 472)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - investigation requests & reports (551 - 600) through Investigation #571. (Box 473)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - investigation #661 through Synanon v. Hearst - request to produce log. (Box 474)
  - Timelines for court case [unidentified] - 3 items [OVERSIZE BOX]. (Box 475)
  - List of California counties that had articles re Synanon through Synanon v. Hearst - discovery U. - plaintiffs' request to produce. (Box 476)
  - Synanon v. Hearst - discovery - correspondence through Holsinger, William. (Box 477)
  - Hernandez, Olga through 5113. (Box 478)
  - Haynesworth, Robb - miscellaneous through Gutman, Jeremiah. (Box 479)
  - Gross, Richard - documents shown to witness during December 1986 - January 1987 through Gross, R. - testimony re witness. (Box 480)
  - Gross, Richie through Gross, Richard - testimony re witness - Synanon v. ABC - fellowship files. (Box 481)
  - SSM literature project - schools literature through CED quotes - fellowship files. (Box 381)
  - Mini-fellowships through Summaries and reports. (Box 382)
- Audio PR Spot Tapes
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Special equipment will be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Synanon commercials through Wild spot. (Box 275)
  - Public service - wild spot through Synanon public service spot -, January 23, 1976. (Box 276)
  - Synanon public service spot (folder 1 of 2) through Synanon public service spot - C. Downs, May 30, 1975. (Box 277)
  - Production tribe tape (folder 1 of 2) through Grok general meeting. (Box 278)
  - 4 reels - public service spots through 4 reels - public service spots, June 23, 1976 June 23, 1976 / July 11, 1972. (Box 279)
  - Public service spots January 23, 1976 - 4 reels through Public service spots January 23, 1976 - 4 reels. (Box 280)
- Betty D.
  - Betty's Book
    - The Betty Dederich Foundation through Quotes by and from Betty Dederich. (Box 24)
    - Quotes about and from Betty Dederich through Betty's season book #10 - annual stockholder's report, 1966. (Box 25)
    - Betty's season book #10 - Synanon game: red room (surgery on orgasm) through No time for Yeah But - complete set. (Box 26)
  - Biography
    - Out card (Wilber interview) through Reynolds, Ed (rough drafts). (Box 41)
    - Betty Dederich: Synanon interview with Marge Sorkin - through Betty Dederich resource material: papers by others., July 1974 (Box 42)
    - Betty Dederich resource material: for biography through Betty's day game circle - the strip -, April 1978. (Box 43)
    - Transcript: Betty D ceremony - Washington, D.C. - through Women in Synanon., April 1978 (Box 44)
  - Business Files
    - Betty D through KL - Synanon archives - publications. (Box 44)
    - KL - Betty D slides through Betty Dederich of Synanon (bound manuscript). (Box 45)
  - Chron Files
    - Microfilm - files - #1 - 81 through, August 1961-May 1977 December 1972. (Box 22)
    - through, January 1973-February 1973 April 1975. (Box 23)
    - through, May 1975 May 1977. (Box 24)
  - I'm Betty D - No time for yeah but
    - Betty Dederich of Synanon (bound manuscript) through To the women. (Box 46)
    - Ode to Chuck through Poetry drafts - unused - No room for yeah buts - file #1. (Box 47)
    - Poetry drafts - unused - No room for yeah buts - file #2 through The new prophets - No room for yeah buts. (Box 48)
    - Women's lib - No room for yeah buts through To Chuck Jr - No room for yeah buts. (Box 49)
    - In the Synanon game - Take care of me - No room for yeah buts through Betty D. (Box 50)
  - Mud Files
    - Mud file index through Mud service: philosophy and education. (Box 20)
    - Outside PR through Mud circ. copies. (Box 21)
    - Mud circ. through Kathy Lebel: chrons - Betty Quist beginning, July 24-August 15, 1975 March 1, 1976. (Box 22)
  - People Files
    - Adams, Pat (aka Binns) through Ciampa, Joanna Lee. (Box 16)
    - Clark, Ernestine through Green, Edna. (Box 17)
    - Green, Sharon through Middleton, Billie. (Box 18)
    - Migacz, Cheriot through Starr, Lois. (Box 19)
    - Stefenel, Ellen through Yettra, Maury and Phyllis. (Box 20)
  - Things File
    - File index through Breeders (includes Hatcherey, etc.)., 1975 (Box 26)
    - Career apparel through Christmas party: Home Place, 1976. (Box 27)
    - Saturday night party through Operation bootstrap. (Box 28)
    - Game and miscellaneous notes through Requests, suggestions, preliminary plans. (Box 29)
    - General correspondence through IDCA: applications. (Box 30)
    - IDCA: correspondence through Staff meeting notes - - Santa Monica., October 4, 1966 (Box 31)
    - Staff meeting notes - - Santa Monica through Ouija sessions -, November 11, 1966 December 1976-July 1968. (Box 32)
    - Ouija sessions - through Bank of America Point Reyes - checking account., May 1969-August 1976 (Box 33)
    - Bank statements - Joseph Magnin's through School children's letters. (Box 34)
    - School through Subscription information. (Box 35)
    - Synanon design through Wedding festival - couples (#2 of 2)., 1975 (Box 36)
    - Wedding festival - guests and housing through Women, study of., 1975 (Box 37)
    - Women's activities reports - Tomales Bay through Women. (Box 38)
  - Transcript Files
    - Five O'Clock shadow - Making a commitment - Chisler's stew - through The Synanon process - through, January 1975 May 1975 1974-1978. (Box 38)
    - Betty fires up SM - Five O'Clock shadow - through Intercharge on missions - Home Place - through, May 1975 May 1976 1974-1978. (Box 39)
    - Out card (S game - marriage) through Betty D ceremony (partial transcript) - through, April 1978 1974-1978. (Box 40)
  - Alpha
    - A through H - I. (Box 14)
    - J - K through R. (Box 15)
    - S through X - Y - Z. (Box 16)
- Bulletin Boards, 1973-1974
  - Bulletin boards - through Bulletin boards -, June 1973 October 1973. (Box 108)
  - Bulletin boards - through Bulletin boards -, November 1973 April 1974. (Box 109)
  - Bulletin boards - through Bulletin boards -, May 1974 August 1974. (Box 110)
  - Bulletin boards - through Bulletin boards -, September 1974 June 1974. (Box 111)
- CED
  - Alpha Active Continued
    - Mummert, Thad through Roberts, Elliot. (Box 538)
    - Roberts, Jack through Schiff family correspondence. (Box 539)
    - Schutz, Shari through Speert, Dennis. (Box 540)
    - Stallone, John through Walker, Portie. (Box 541)
    - Walker, Portie through Yettra, Maury and Phyllis. (Box 542)
  - Educational Tools Project
    - Educational tools files through Dichotomies. (Box 50)
    - Education through Massive doses. (Box 51)
    - Educational tools manual copy through Rough notes. (Box 52)
    - Interface: Simon, Simon & Blessing - an experiment in education - through Transcript (excerpt) - morning court -, 1971 June 1977. (Box 53)
    - Transcript (excerpt) - morning court - through Reel-to-reel tape: Think table excerpts (4 of 4)., July 1977 (Box 54)
    - Transcript - X step basic drill #4 - overlap - through Zen master., September 1970 (Box 55)
  - Biography
    - Paper: transcription of the Unicept tape through Transcript: X step basic drill #6 - getting into motion -, October 1970. (Box 55)
    - Log: Unicept posse workshop - reel 2 of 2 - through CED's LSD experience., February 1970 (Box 56)
    - Out card (transcript: Chuck Dederich's religious conversion - ) through CED draft., October 1978 (Box 57)
    - Out card (CED conversion) through Grey Thompson interviews (#1 & 2) - rough transcripts-, 1978. (Box 58)
  - Chron, 1965-1981
    - CED chrons miscellaneous - through CED chron file -, 1959-1966 1965-1967. (Box 542)
    - Chron file - through Chron file -, January 1968-March 1968 October-December 1972. (Box 543)
    - CED chron - through CED chron -, July-September 1972 July-September 1975. (Box 544)
    - Chron - through CED chrons -, October-December 1975 1982-1987. (Box 545)
  - Literature
    - Anti-hustling meeting with CED and Matt Rand through By-pass #4 - being and becoming. (Box 202)
    - Being and becoming through CED holds court. (Box 203)
    - Contracts through Excerpt #9. (Box 204)
    - Excerpts - general through Monday night game - introduction. (Box 205)
    - The key through CED talks on rearing children. (Box 206)
    - Religious conversion experience through You've got to take that walk alone. (Box 207)
    - Synanon family report through Holy war battle - Westport connecticut., 1976 (Box 208)
  - People Alpha Active - DEI-L
    - Deissler, Karl J., M.D. through CED - Garrett Family - Glenda, Alice, Debbie and Mike. (Box 533)
    - CED - Garrett, Dorothy (Nee Salant) through CED - Griggs, David. (Box 534)
    - CED - Gross, Jan, M.D. (aka Schwartz) through Kaplan, Ellis. (Box 535)
    - Kaufman, Jon through Lustky, Cyril. (Box 536)
  - People Alpha Active - Mac-Sm
    - Macartney, Margo through Mullen, Rod. (Box 537)
  - People Files - Active
    - Seawall - meanderings of a dog robber through CED holiday cards & responses, December 1985. (Box 494)
    - CED birthday cards & responses through LAIR: Brush, Helen., March 1989 (Box 495)
    - Bulles, Dick through Cook, Pamela (aka Anderson). (Box 496)
    - CED - Cook, Ron, President through Betty Dederich - condolence cards & letters., February 1975-May 1975 (Box 497)
    - Betty D. memorabilia through CED love match. (Box 498)
    - Pilot license through CED - Dederich, Sherry. (Box 499)
  - People Files - Closed
    - Adams, Pat (nee Binns) through Carter, Alice (nee Gripps). (Box 499)
    - Cherkas, Marshall S. through Endore, Guy - call me Shakespeare. (Box 500)
    - Endore, Guy - Humanist article through Heaphy, Richard. (Box 501)
    - Henry, E.G. through Levitt, Mortimer. (Box 502)
    - Linton, Barbara through Norten, Allen. (Box 503)
    - Notkins, Matt through Stevens, R.W. (Box 504)
    - Starso, Mike ) through Miscellaneous., (November 1971 (Box 505)
  - Things Files - General
    - Home Place facility - general through Oakland - general. (Box 491)
    - Oakland game club reports through Santa Monica - game club. (Box 492)
    - Santa Monica - general through Stew files - Tomales Bay. (Box 493)
    - Dissipation reports through Seawall - meandering of a dog robber. (Box 494)
  - Things Files - Inactive, A-G
    - Aerobics through CED Synanon archives. (Box 481)
    - CED archives / CED publications - Simon, etc. through Buttons. (Box 482)
    - Chairman's conference - - reports through CED communications wire schedules -, January 1972 1974-1975. (Box 483)
    - Communications - audio tape through Cube, the. (Box 484)
    - Cube club through Educational staff seminar visits to Synanon -, 1973. (Box 485)
    - Education, Board of (Vickman) through First Thirty partnership. (Box 486)
    - Food services through Graphics. (Box 487)
    - Staff meeting notes - through SOS - miscellaneous correspondence., January 1966 (Box 488)
    - Synanon industries - Gulf station through OEO literature. (Box 489)
    - Non-California - State of Colorado through Synanon industries - weekly sales reports. (Box 490)
  - Things H-R
    - Habitat through Home place review file -, June 1973-December 1973. (Box 521)
    - Home place review file - through Lifestyler study., January 1, 1974 (Box 522)
    - Look Magazine through Pedro Soto day #2. (Box 523)
    - Pedro Soto day III through CED - Public relations news bulletins. (Box 524)
    - Public safety and connect logs Tomales - through Reliable weekend -, September 1975 November 17-21, 1976. (Box 525)
  - Things H-Y
    - CED - reliable investors - the next 200 through CED - resources (supply). (Box 526)
    - CED - reliable investors - the next 200 through CED - resources (supply). (Box 526)
    - Responses to letters - re LSR interviews through Yale University. (Box 527)
  - Things Inactive
    - Tape survey through Sunset house. (Box 532)
    - S.C.R.A.M. through S.D.C. - survey of living/working. (Box 528)
    - Service Station through Stew complex CED -, 1975. (Box 529)
    - Stew complex. through CED - Synanon International - Germany., 1974 (Box 530)
    - Synanon logo through CED - Time Incorporated. (Box 531)
  - Transcript Files., 1960-1970
    - CJD limited edition photos project through Log - an introduction -, October 17, 1962. (Box 224)
    - Blackboard counselors through Indoctrination of C. Lauricello. (Box 225)
    - Transcript - new role of women - through I love Chuck in 25 words - tape #142., January 2, 1963 (Box 226)
    - Log - Huntley council - through Transcript - Operation By-pass #2 -, October 7, 1963 March 11, 1965. (Box 227)
    - By-pass transcripts through Log - Operation By-pass #7 -, April 29, 1965. (Box 228)
    - Transcript - Operation By-pass #8 - through Transcript - SFVSC lecture #3 - Ten questions -, May 6, 1965 January 26, 1965. (Box 229)
    - Transcript - SFVSC lecture #3 - Ten questions - through Transcript - making love -, October 26, 1965 March 19, 1966. (Box 230)
    - Transcript - SFVSC lecture #17 - role or not through Out card - CED - first arts committee meeting. (Box 231)
    - Log - CED discuss Del March acquisition at press conference through Transcript - the realized thought -, January 1, 1968 July 1, 1968. (Box 232)
    - Transcript - bald head symbiology - through Log - CED & Betty in the stew - stew -, July 1, 1968 July 12, 1968. (Box 233)
    - Stews, scribes and spectators - through Out card CED, Betty & DLG in stew -, July 13, 1968 August 23, 1968. (Box 234)
    - Dan's dissipation - through Transcript - interthink with mamas and papas -, August 8, 1969 January 7, 1970. (Box 235)
    - Log - innerthink - through Regent's dissipation -, August 24, 1968 July 23, 1969. (Box 236)
    - Mamas and papas' tribe interthink - through New emphasis on health - reel 1 of 1 - 20, January 1970 April 1965. (Box 237)
  - Transcript Files., 1970-1975
    - Transcript - unicept posse - overlaps & paradox - through CED talks about friendship -, September 23, 1970 May 26, 1971. (Box 237)
    - CED in stew - through Dorothy in stew -, June 3, 1971 September 3, 1971. (Box 238)
    - CED in stew with Joe Scalza & Lenny Feiner - through CED interviewed by Jean Debelle -, September 6, 1971 September 6, 1972. (Box 239)
    - Transcript - First academy trip opening address - through Log - CED - straddle excerpt - employee -, September 22, 1972 April 24, 1973. (Box 240)
    - Log - CED meeting - straddle bit - through Transcript - directors' conference -, April 26, 1973 August 13, 1973. (Box 241)
    - Directors' conference - through Foundation stew #3 -, August 13, 1973 December 23, 1973. (Box 242)
    - Keynote address - Chuck Dederich - through CED in community -, January 4, 1974 March 19, 1974. (Box 243)
    - CED in community stew - through CED - contract game is evil -, March 20, 1974 July 10, 1974. (Box 244)
    - Discussion of basic training corps - through Log - Monday night game -, July 11, 1974 September 9, 1974. (Box 245)
    - Executive meeting - through Executive meeting -, September 13, 1974 December 19, 1974. (Box 246)
    - Executive meeting - through Executive directors' meeting -, December 20, 1974 April 29, 1975. (Box 247)
  - Transcript Files., 1975-1977
    - Education & interchanges through Betty D story. (Box 248)
    - Badger executive couples game - through Breaking away from the Synanon community -, May 28, 1975 September 2, 1975. (Box 249)
    - Documentation project - meeting #2 - designing the religious life through Pedro/Soto III -, January 9, 1976. (Box 250)
    - Transcript - Robbie Robinson's life story - through Transcript - chairman's conference - education meeting -, January 10, 1976 April 9, 1976. (Box 251)
    - Transcript - morning meeting - Betty Dederich on the PX - through Transcript - CED session -, April 16, 1976 October 22, 1976. (Box 252)
    - CED lunch - Jenkins love match - through Transcript - CED session - act as if / free will -, October 22, 1976 March 1, 1977. (Box 253)
    - Morning court - through Transcript - excerpts from board of directors' game -, March 9, 1977 April 24, 1977. (Box 254)
    - Board of directors' meeting - through Morning court -, April 25, 1977 June 2, 1977. (Box 255)
    - Synanon people - through Dinner game circle -, June 3, 1977 July 1, 1977. (Box 256)
    - CED court - through Stockholders' meeting & game -, July 1, 1977 August 20, 1977. (Box 257)
    - Outcard - stockholders meeting and game. through Game - the new marriage., August 20, 1977 (Box 258)
    - CED think table - through Transcript - Saturday night game, October 13, 1977 November 19, 1977. (Box 259)
  - Transcript Files., 1977-1981
    - AP interview through CED session, Novermber 23, 1977 January 3, 1978. (Box 260)
    - Eight group game through CED Jr. runs his game -, January 4, 1978 February 3, 1978. (Box 261)
    - Think table through Celebration of life ceremony for Devon Green, February 4, 1978 April 21, 1981. (Box 262)
- Chairman's Office Chrons -, 1971-1977
  - Founder's office chrons - through Chairman's office chrons -, November 1977 March 1977. (Box 547)
  - Chairman's office chrons - through Chairman's office chrons -, February 1977 March-April 1976. (Box 548)
  - Chairman's office chrons - through Chairman's office chron -, January 1 February 29, 1976 March 1975. (Box 549)
  - Chairman's office chrons - through Chairman's office chrons -, February 1975 October-December 1971. (Box 550)
  - Chairman's office chrons - through Chairman's office chrons - Box not full., July-September 1971 January 1 - June 30, 1971 (Box 551)
- Development Files
  - ADGAP through Archives - video equipment inventory. (Box 2)
  - Archives - videos requested and received through Betty - University Writers conference, August 1980. (Box 3)
  - Board correspondence through Office chron, 1980. (Box 4)
  - S.S. chrons through Divinity. (Box 5)
  - Education through Equipment - manuals. (Box 6)
  - Equipment - Sony catalogs & brochures through Forms - tape analysis sheets. (Box 7)
  - Forms through Grants - innovation in management. (Box 8)
  - CED collective works grant - time sheets through Media. (Box 9)
  - Microgame - correspondence through Newsletters & brochures - Association for Humanistic Psychology. (Box 10)
  - Newsletters & brochures - miscellaneous through Literature - Growth center brochures. (Box 11)
  - Literature - miscellaneous through SRI - Barbara Newmark. (Box 12)